个人原创字幕
制作人：A Redpill
了解更多影片细节，请访问The Matrix Wiki
https://matrix.fandom.com
[创作声明]
所有添加的情节注释，均检索自Matrix Wiki词条，译者仅加以翻译和精简；
但针对存在多种解读的情节，仅展示了译者较为认可的一种；
多处典故解读，则引用自圣经和合本或新译本，以及维基百科英文版
黑 客 帝 国
THE MATRIX
重 装 上 阵
R E L O A D E D
明天见
See you tomorrow.
哦，上帝啊！
Oh, my God!
我进来了
I'm in.
我们就快到了
We're almost there.
-长官，你有把握吗？ -我说过，不会出问题的
-Sir, are you sure about this? -I told you, we're going to be all right.
我明白，长官 只是我观测到，那儿有大量的哨兵活动
I understand, sir. It's just that I'm scoping some serious sentinel activity up here.
-林克 -长官？
-Link. -Yes, sir?
考虑到你的情况，我还是不能明白……
Given your situation, I can't say I fully understand your reasons...
你为什么要志愿到我的舰上工作
...for volunteering to operate onboard my ship.
不过，如果你想继续干下去，我有件事需要你去做
However, if you wish to continue to do so, I must ask you to do one thing.
什么事，长官？
What's that, sir?
要信任我
To trust me.
是，长官 我会的
Yes, sir. I will, sir.
-我是说，我一定做到 -但愿如此
-I mean, I do, sir. -I hope so.
现在将主电源重新接到硬盘驱动器上，准备广播信号吧
Now repatch the main AC to the hard drives and stand by to broadcast.
是，长官
Yes, sir.
还是睡不着吗？
Still can't sleep?
想谈谈吗？
You wanna talk?
只是做了个噩梦
They're just dreams.
如果你是在担心什么……
If you're afraid of something....
我只是希望……
I just wish....
希望知道自己该去做哪些事
I wish I knew what I'm supposed to do.
仅此而已
That's all.
我真希望能知道
I just wish I knew.
她会和你联系的 别再担心了
She's gonna call. Don't worry.
找到你们了
Here you are.
-我们该出发了吗？ -已经要迟到了
-Are we ready to go? -We're already late.
这些地热成像图证实了冥王号发回的最后一条讯息
These geotherms confirm the last transmission of the Osiris.
机器正在钻洞
The machines are digging.
它们要从地表一直挖到锡安
They're boring from the surface down to Zion.
-妈的 -它们想避开我们的整个外围防御
-Mother -They'll avoid the entire perimeter defense.
它们移动的速度有多快？
How fast are they moving?
-控制中心估计速度是100米/每小时 -该死
-Control estimates their descent at 100 meters an hour. -Shit.
-现在挖了多深？ -大约2000米
-How deep are they? -Almost 2000 meters.
-冥王号的观测结果如何？ -他们不可能是准的
-What about the scans from the Osiris? -They can't be accurate.
-但也可能是对的 -这不可能
-They may be. -It's not possible.
这就意味着有25万乌贼哨兵
That'd mean there are a quartermillion sentinels out there.
-没错 -那不可能
-That's right. -That can't be.
为什么不可能？
Why not?
一只乌贼对付一个人类，锡安的男女老幼都算进去
A sentinel for every man, woman and child in Zion.
对我来说，那完全符合机器的思维逻辑
That sounds exactly like the thinking of a machine to me.
墨菲斯，你能来真是太好了
Morpheus, glad you could join us.
奈奥比
Niobe.
抱歉我来迟了
My apologies to all.
你们无疑也明白，要找到安全的广播位置越来越困难了
But as you are undoubtedly aware it's become increasingly difficult to locate a secure broadcast position.
-最好的位置都被乌贼占了 -它们把主管道都给挤满了
-Squiddies got our best spots. -Main lines are crawling with them.
如果奈奥比是对的，72小时内它们的数量会超过25万
And if Niobe's right, in 72 hours there's gonna be a quartermillion more.
我们应该如何应对呢？
What are we gonna do about it?
我们按照洛克指挥官的命令去做……
We're gonna do what Commander Lock ordered us to do.
撤出广播信号的深度，返回锡安
We'll evacuate broadcast level and return to Zion.
指挥官有没有什么对策来抵御二十五万哨兵呢？
And does the commander have a plan for stopping 250,000 sentinels?
战略仍在制定中
A strategy is still being formulated.
相信如此
I'm sure it is.
（史密斯的车牌号是IS5416，对应圣经《以塞亚书》第54章16节 Isaiah 54:16：
"Behold, I have created the smith who blows the fire of coals, and produces a weapon for its purpose. I have also created the ravager to destroy;"
“看啊，是我造了扇旺炭火、
铸造合用兵器的铁匠(Smith)，
是我造了毁灭者”）
那你认为我们应该做什么，墨菲斯？
What do you think we should do, Morpheus?
-我们本该听命行事…… -怎么了？
-We should proceed as ordered... -What is it?
-不知道 -但是，我必须向你们中的一个请求帮助……
I don't know. ...however, I must ask one of you for help.
你们中有些人信我所信，有些人不信
Some of you believe as I believe, some of you do not. But those of you that do...
但那些即使不信的人也得承认：我们已经到了抗争的最后关头
...know we are nearing the end of our struggle.
救世主预言很快就会应验 但在那之前……
The prophecy will be fulfilled soon. But before it can be...
必须求教先知
...the Oracle must be consulted.
（注意墙上的涂鸦
最简单的解读方式是，意指 圣经 旧约 诗篇 25:19：
“看啊，我的仇敌众多，他们都痛恨我”）
如果我们现在回去充电的话...
If we return and recharge now...
36小时内即可返回，远早于机器挖到这个深度
...we can be back in 36 hours, well before the machines reach this depth.
你知道自己是要求什么吗？
Do you understand what you're asking?
我是要求有一艘战舰留在这里
I am asking that one ship remain here in our place...
以备先知与我们取得联系
...just in case the Oracle should attempt to contact us.
放屁 你这是要我们当中的一艘船去抗命
Bullshit. You're asking one of us to disobey a direct order.
没错，我是 不过大家都很清楚，我们中的大部分之所以来到这里……
That's right, I am. But we well know that the reason most of us are here...
就是因为有叛逆倾向
...is because of our affinity for disobedience.
如果你回锡安后，指挥官把你投入监狱怎么办？
And what happens when you get to Zion and the commander throws you in the stockade?
他不会
He won't.
见鬼， 墨菲斯，你真是顽固不化
Goddamn it, Morpheus, you ain't never gonna change.
那好吧，我可以留下 我倒要看看你要怎么打破僵局
Shit, I'll do it just to see what Deadbolt does to you.
给你36个小时
You got 36 hours.
我找尼奥
I'm looking for Neo.
-没说听过这个人 -我有东西给他
Never heard of him. I have something for him.
一件礼物
A gift.
知道吗，是他让我自由了
You see, he set me free.
好吧，随你怎么说 现在滚吧
Fine, whatever. Now piss off.
-什么人？ -你怎么知道有人找你的？
-Who was that? -How did you know someone was here?
他要给你这个
He gave you this.
他说是你让他自由了
He said you set him free.
一切都还好吧，长官？
Is everything all right, sir?
会议结束了，回你们的船上去吧
The meeting is over. Retreat to your exits.
-特工就要来了 -特工？
-Agents are coming. -Agents?
快走
Go.
嗨，伙计们
Hiya, fellas.
就是他 那个变异
It's him. The anomaly.
-还要继续吗？ -是的
-Do we proceed? -Yes.
-他依然... -只是人类
-He is still... -Only human.
升级了
Upgrades.
-一切都按预期进行 -是的
-That went as expected. -Yes.
跟以前发生的一模一样
It's happening exactly as before.
好吧，也不尽然
Well, not exactly.
-那儿发生了什么，林克？ -我搞不明白
-What happened at that, Link? -I can't figure it out,sir.
突然凭空出现了特工
Agents just came out of nowhere.
接着代码全都变得怪异了 加密模式是我从没见过的
Then the code got all weird. Encryption I've never seen.
-尼奥没事吧？ -没事 见鬼，你真该亲眼看看的
-Is Neo okay? -Okay? Shit, you should've seen him.
他现在在哪儿？
Where is he now?
正在扮演超人呢
He's doing his Superman thing.
你去哪儿了？
Where are you?
尼布加尼撒号即将进站，请求使用通过三号入口
This is the Nebuchadnezzar on approach, requesting access through Gate Three.
尼布加尼撒号，这里是锡安控制台 保持当前航速，等候指令
Nebuchadnezzar, this is Zion Control. Maintain present velocity and stand by.
收到
Roger that, Control.
这里是锡安基地控制台，请求立即解除三号入口的封锁
This is Control requesting immediate standdown of arms at Gate Three.
尼布加尼撒号准备进站 三号入口即将打开
We have the Nebuchadnezzar on approach. Let's open her up.
尼布加尼撒号，准许你们由三号入口进入第七停机坪
Nebuchadnezzar, You are cleared through Gate Three to Bay Seven.
收到
Roger that, Control.
门已打开，床已铺好 欢迎回家
Door's open, bed's made. Welcome home.
回家真好
No place like it.
收到了 锡安控制台，准备关闭三号入口
Roger that, Control. Zion Control, stand by for Gate Three lockdown.
尼布加尼撒号已经降落 七号停机坪
The Nebuchadnezzar is down. Bay Seven.
明白
Understood.
米孚安舰长
Captain Mifune.
墨菲斯舰长
Captain Morpheus.
你是来押我去监狱的吗，舰长？
Are you here to escort me to the stockade, captain?
-我无意挑起争端 -洛克指挥官命令你……
-I'm just here to keep the peace. -Commander Lock demands
要求你立刻去见他，长官！
Requests your immediate counsel, sir.
-林克 -长官？
-Link. -Sir?
我要让战舰尽快做好启程准备
I want the ship ready to go as soon as possible.
明白，长官
Understood, sir.
他俩之间发生过什么吗？ 墨菲斯和洛克？
What is it between them? Morpheus and Lock?
-因为奈奥比 -奈奥比舰长？
-Niobe. -Captain Niobe?
她过去和墨菲斯在一起，现在却和洛克好上了
She used to be with Morpheus. Now she's with Lock.
出了什么事？
What happened?
墨菲斯见过先知后，一切都变了
Morpheus went to the Oracle. After that, everything changed.
好吧，她是做得到
Yeah, she can do that.
尼奥
Neo!
-哦，不是吧 -他怎么每次都知道？
-Oh, no. -How does he always know?
他就没别的事情可做吗？
Doesn't he have anything better to do?
谁叫你救了他一命呢
You know what they say about the life you save.
不是我救了他
I didn't save his life.
（the Kid 是《黑客帝国动画版》The Animatrix 中,《少年故事》主角
他跟尼奥联系后被特工追捕，走投无路之下选择跳楼自杀，结果竟然在真实世界里醒来
所以算是自己救了自己）
你好，尼奥
Hiya, Neo.
崔妮蒂 林克
Trinity, Link. Hey.
-你能回来真是太好了 -谢谢 回来真好
-It's great to have you back. -Thanks. It's good to be back.
-我来帮你拿好吗？ -不，我自己背得动
-Can I carry that for you? -No, I can carry my own bag.
-崔妮蒂？ -我能行
-Trinity? -I'm fine.
-那你帮忙拿这些吧 -好的，当然可以，林克
-You can carry these. -Yeah, sure, Link.
你知道的，明年我就够年龄成为舰员了，对吧？
Hey, you know, next year I'm old enough to join a crew, right?
对此我已经想了很久，我已经决定……
I've been thinking about it, and I've made my decision.
我猜……
Let me guess.
我要加入尼布加尼撒号
I want to join the Nebuchadnezzar.
我知道墨菲斯还没找到舰员来填补其他岗位 除了你那个，林克
I know Morpheus hasn't filled the other crew position, except for you, Link.
当然，他有自己的考量……
I'm sure he has reasons...
不过我越想就越觉得，这应该就是天意
...but the more I think about it, the more I think it's meant to be.
你知道的，命中注定
You know, it's fate.
-我能来这儿全是因为你，尼奥 -我告诉过你，孩子，是你主动找到了我，不是我去找你
You're the reason I'm here, Neo. -I told you, kid, you found me. I didn't find you.
但毕竟是你把我解救出来的 你救了我
I know, but you got me out. You saved me.
是你自己救了自己
You saved yourself.
-墨菲斯 -洛克指挥官
-Morpheus. -Commander Lock.
我其他舰长谈过了 我想给你个机会好好解释解
I spoke to the other captains. I wanted to offer you a chance to explain your actions.
我不认为我的所作所为需要任何解释
I wasn't aware that my actions required any explanation.
我下达了直接命令让你们返回锡安
You were given a direct order to return to Zion.
-我返回了 -可你让一艘战舰留在原地
-I did. -But you asked for one ship to remain behind.
本该是我留下，但是我的战舰需要充电
I would have stayed, but I needed to recharge my ship.
所以你是承认自己公然违抗命令
So you admit to a direct contravention of your duty.
可是指挥官，我们需要有人留在矩阵里以备先知的联络
Commander, we need a presence inside the Matrix to await contact from the Oracle.
我不想听那些鬼话！
I don't want to hear that shit!
我才不在乎什么先知、预言或是救世主！
I don't care about oracles or prophecies or messiahs!
我只关心一事，那就是要阻止敌人毁灭这座城
I care about one thing: Stopping that army from destroying this city.
要做到这一点，所有士兵都必须服从我的命令
To do that I need soldiers to obey my orders.
无意冒犯，指挥官，只有一种办法可以拯救我们的城市
With all due respect, commander, there is only one way to save our city.
是什么？
How?
-尼奥 -见鬼去吧，墨菲斯！
-Neo. -Goddamn it, Morpheus！
不是人人都信你所信
Not everyone believes what you believe.
我所相信的，无需他人同信
My beliefs do not require them to.
今晚有个集会 大家可以畅所欲言，很多人吓坏了
There's a gathering tonight. Everyone's talking. A lot of people are scared.
这么多战舰集结的情形已经多年未见了
No one remembers the last time so many ships were docked.
-一定有什么事情要发生，对吗？一件大事 -嘿
-Something is happening, isn't it, Something big? -Hey.
不是什么事都可以告诉你，所以别再问了
We're not allowed to say anything, so stop asking.
老天呐，回家的感觉真好
Goddamn, it's good to be home.
我将向议会提议解除你的职务
I'm recommending the council that you be removed from duty.
那当然是你的特权，指挥官
That is, of course, your prerogative, commander.
如果有权决定的是我，舰长，你今后再也别想踏上战舰一步！
If it were up to me, captain, you wouldn't set foot on a ship for the rest of your life.
那我得庆幸：你并没有决定权
Then I am grateful that it is not up to you.
-哈曼议员 -指挥官
-Councillor Hamann. -Commander.
-舰长 -议员
-Captain. -Councillor.
议会要求我，在今晚的神庙集会上演讲
Council's asked me to speak tonight at the temple gathering.
舰队的集结和持续的流言必须予以解释
The presence of the fleet and the persistence of rumors must be addressed.
人民必须被告知发生了什么
The people must be told what is happening.
当然要解释的，议员
Of course, councillor.
不过请允许我提议，对某些具体细节作斟酌处理
But might I advise a level of discretion concerning specific details.
-我们不希望引起过度恐慌 -说的很对
-We do not wish to start a panic. -Quite right.
恐慌不是人人都想要的
A panic is not what anyone wants.
你呢，舰长？ 有什么建议吗？
What about you, captain? What would you advise?
必须告知真相 没人会对真相恐慌，因为我们没有什么好怕的
The truth. No one will panic, because there is nothing to fear.
敌人将永远无法踏进锡安的大门
That army will never reach the gates of Zion.
-你何以如此确定呢？ -就以我们的亲眼所见，议员
What makes you so sure? Consider what we have seen, councillor.
就凭过去六个月，我们解放了比过去六年还多的意识
Consider that in the past six months, we have freed more minds than in six years.
这次进攻是孤注一掷之举
This attack is an act of desperation.
我相信，预言不久就会应验，战争很快就将结束
I believe very soon the prophecy will be fulfilled and this war will end.
希望你是对的，舰长
I hope you're right, captain.
我相信它并非某种“愿景”，议员
I do not believe it to be a matter of hope, councillor.
它只是，尚未发生的事实
It is simply a matter of time.
我到了
My stop.
回头见
See you soon.
希望不要太快
Hopefully not too soon.
走吧，孩子，他们俩还有事情要做
Let's go, kid. These two got things to do.
你跟我想的一样吗？
Are you thinking what I'm thinking?
如果你也觉得刚才太他妈漫长，那我们想的一样
I am if you're thinking this elevator is too damns long.
-战舰需要充多久的电？ -24到30个小时
-How long do we charge the Neb? -Twentyfour, maybe 30 hours.
真是我这辈子听过的最好的消息
Some people go their entire lives without hearing news that good.
尼奥，求你了 我儿子雅各在gnosis号上
（希腊语 gnosis 意为 knowledge）
Neo, please, I have a son, Jacob, aboard the Gnosis.
-求你多多关照他 -我会尽力的
-Please, watch over him. -I'll try.
我女儿在lcarus号上
（lcarus 即伊卡洛斯，希腊神话中的悲剧人物
代达罗斯与伊卡洛斯父子使用蜡质羽翼逃离克里特岛时，伊卡洛斯飞的太靠近太阳，最终落水而亡
悲伤的代达罗斯飞回家乡后，将自己那对蜡翼悬挂在阿波罗神殿里，从此不再飞翔）
I have a daughter on the lcarus.
不，别走
No, wait.
没关系，他们需要你
It's all right. They need you.
-可我需要你 -我知道
-I need you. -I know.
我们还有时间
There's time.
我的小猫咪在哪里？
Where's my puss?
林克叔叔
Hey! Uncle Link!
天呐
God!
林克叔叔
Uncle Link!
我的老天，都长这么大了
Oh, my God! You're so huge!
-应该是你们来抱我的！ -不要！
-You should be picking me up! -No!
-好不好？ -好吧
-Yeah! -Okay!
好了吗？ 那行啊
Okay? All right.
让我们一起使劲，好不好？
Now, we're gonna have to work together here, okay?
一、二、三，起！
One, two, three, lift!
老天，你给他们吃什么了？
Oh, my God! What are you feeding these two?
好了，孩子们，该睡觉了
Come on, kids. It's time to go.
-嗨，凯丝 -嗨
-Hey, Cas. -Hey.
-真高兴你回家，林克 -回家真好
-Good to have you home, Link. -Good to be home.
你对她可要小心点儿
You be careful with her.
别担心我了，该担心的是他
Don't worry about me. He's the one that's gonna get it.
该出门了，你们两个，咱们走吧
Out the door! Both of you, march!
拜拜
Bye! Bye!
我该怎么着？
I'm gonna get what?
其他战舰回家的次数是尼布加尼撒号的两到三倍
Every ship up there's been home two, even three times more than the Nebuchadnezzar.
好啦，姬伊 我们不是不谈这个了吗
Come on, Zee. I thought we were past this.
-只有等你换了战舰，我们才能不谈这个 -我不能这么做
-We will get pass this when you start operating another ship.
-I can't do that.
-为什么？ -你是知道的
-Why? -You know why.
要是多泽知道我的感受，当初就不会让你这么做了
If Dozer knew how I felt, he wouldn't have asked you to do this.
可能吧，不过太迟了
Maybe. But it's too late now.
我做过承诺，有些承诺是不可以违背的
I made a promise, and some promises can't be unmade.
-这不公平 -没人说过这世上很公平
-It's not fair. -Nobody said it was gonna be.
你觉得我回来了可多泽走了，对凯丝来说公平吗？
You think Cas thinks it's fair that I'm here and Dozer's not?
我在那艘船上失去了两个兄弟，林克
I lost two brothers to that ship, Link.
我好害怕
I'm afraid of it.
害怕你也被它害死
I'm afraid it's gonna take you too.
不会的
It won't.
你怎么敢说不会？
How can you say that to me?
是因为墨菲斯
Because of Morpheus.
他对我说过，这就是最后一战，而且很快就会结束
Because of what he's told me. He said that this is it, that it will be over soon.
-林克，墨菲斯就是疯了 -一点不假
-Link, Morpheus is crazy. -No doubt.
可是坦克和多泽都相信他 我来告诉你为什么……
But Tank and Dozer believed him. And I'll tell you what...
我上了那条战舰以后，看到了尼奥的所作所为
...after being on that ship and seeing Neo do the things he can do, I gotta say...
我得说：我也开始相信他了
...I'm starting to believe him too.
注意安全，林克
Be careful, Link.
你一定得注意安全
Please be careful.
-已经开始了吗？ -哈曼议员才刚开始祷告呢
-They started yet? -Only Councillor Hamann's opening prayer.
今晚，让荣光归于所有男人和女人
Tonight, let us honor these men and women.
士兵和勇士
These are our soldiers, our warriors.
丈夫和妻子，兄弟和姐妹
These are our husbands and wives, our brothers and sisters...
以及我们的孩子们
...our children.
让我们永远铭记那些牺牲者
Let us remember those that have been lost...
也感谢那些觉醒者
...and let us give thanks for those that have been found...
那些和我们站在了一起的人们
...and who stand here beside us.
下面，我想有请另一个人替我完成这次祷告
Now I would like someone else to close this prayer...
他已经很久没有在这里发言了……
...someone who hasn't spoken here in a long time...
但我相信，他所要讲的将是值得一听的
...but who I believe has something to say that we all need to hear.
下面欢迎墨菲斯
I give you Morpheus.
锡安的子民们！ 听我说！
Zion! Hear me!
你们中的很多人听说的正是事实
It is true what many of you have heard.
机器的军队已经集结，就在我说话的时候……
The machines have gathered an army, and as I speak...
那支大军还在向我们的家园掘进
...that army is drawing nearer to our home.
相信我，我们将面临一段艰难时期
Believe me when I say we have a difficult time ahead of us.
但是，如果我们要为此做好准备，首先要做的必须是放下恐惧！
But if we are to be prepared for it, we must first shed our fear of it.
我现在站在你们面前，没有丝毫的恐惧
I stand here before you now truthfully unafraid.
为什么？
Why?
是因为我相信某些你们不信的事吗？
Because I believe something you do not?
不！
No!
我毫无恐惧地站在这里是因为我记得
I stand here without fear because I remember.
我记得，我还能站在这里不是因为未来的事物……
I remember that I am here not because of the path that lies before me...
而是因为过去的历史！
...but because of the path that lies behind me.
我记得，一百年多年来，我们一直在和机器战斗
I remember that for 100 years we have fought these machines.
我记得，一百多年来，它们不断地派兵毁灭我们
I remember that for 100 years they have sent their armies to destroy us.
经过一个世纪的战争，我记得，最重要是的：
And after a century of war, I remember that which matters most:
我们仍然在此挺立！
We are still here!
今晚……
Tonight...
让我们把这样一条讯息告诉我们的敌人
...Let us send a message to that army.
今晚，我们要让这个洞窟倾覆
Tonight, let us shake this cave.
今晚，我们要让世间万物颤抖
Tonight, let us tremble these halls of earth, steel and stone.
让我们的声音响彻全球
Let us be heard from red core to black sky.
今晚，我们要让敌人明白：
Tonight, let us make them remember:
这里是锡安！我们无所畏惧！
This is Zion and we are not afraid!
我记得一些事
I remember.
我记得你过去经常跳舞
I remember you used to dance.
我记得你跳得，非常好
I remember you were, pretty good.
在这个世上有一些事情，奈奥比舰长……
There are some things in this world, Captain Niobe...
永远不会改变
...that will never change.
奈奥比！
Niobe!
还有一些确实会变
Some things do change.
失陪了
Excuse me.
-我想你 -我知道
-I missed you. -I can tell.
我在想，这里人太多了
I was thinking, everyone is here.
跟我来吧
Follow me.
尼奥，怎么了？
Neo, what is it?
有什么不对吗？
What's wrong?
没关系的，请告诉我
It's okay, you can tell me.
崔妮蒂……
Trinity....
不要害怕
Don't be afraid.
我不能失去你
I can't lose you.
你不会失去我的
You're not gonna lose me.
你感觉到了吗？
You feel this?
我永远不会放手的
I'm never letting go.
晚安，锡安
Good night, Zion.
做个好梦
Sweet dreams.
-你还好吧？ -我没事的
-You all right? -I'll make it.
看到那特工了吗？ 我从没见过那种样子
Did you see that agent? I've never seen anything like that.
别管他了 重要的是这个
It doesn't matter. All that matters is this.
你先来
You first.
-哦，上帝 -叫“史密斯”就好
-Oh, God. -"Smith" will suffice.
-谢谢 -不必客气
-Thank you. -My pleasure.
-不介意有人陪你吧？ -哈曼议员
-Care for some company? -Councillor Hamann.
如果你想一个人呆着，我不勉强
I don't want to intrude if you'd prefer to be alone.
不会的，我大概正需要有人陪着 -那就好
-No, I could probably use some company. -Good.
我也是
So could l.
今晚夜色真美
It's nice tonight.
非常平静
Very calm.
似乎所有人都已经安然入睡了
It feels like everyone is sleeping very peacefully.
并非所有人
Not everyone.
我讨厌睡觉，我每天只睡几个小时
I hate sleeping. I never sleep more than a few hours.
我想是因为，我这辈子的前11年里都在沉睡，现在要用醒着作为补偿
I figure I slept the first 11 years of my life, now I'm making up for it.
-你呢？ -我从来就睡不好
-What about you? -I just haven't been able to sleep much.
-这是个好迹象 -说明什么？
-It's a good sign. -Of what?
表明你实际上，仍属于人类
That you are in fact, still human.
你去过下面的基础设施层吗？
Have you ever been to the engineering level?
我喜欢晚上到那儿去 真是令人震撼
I love to walk there at night. It's quite amazing.
-想去看看吗？ -当然
-Would you like to see it? -Sure.
平时几乎没人来这儿 当然，除非是出了问题
Almost no one comes down here. Unless, of course, there's a problem.
人们就是如此 只要它能正常运转，没人会关心它到底是如何运作的
That's how it is with people. Nobody cares how it works as long as it works.
我喜欢这下面的一切
I like it down here.
我总喜欢提醒自己，正是这些机器让这个城市得以维系
I like to be reminded this city survives because of these machines.
这些机器保障了我们的生存，然而另外一些却要毁灭我们
These machines are keeping us alive while other machines are coming to kill us.
很有意思，不是吗？ 给养生命的能力……
Interesting, isn't it? The power to give life...
-也可以毁灭生命 -我们也有同样的能力
-...and the power to end it. -We have the same power.
是啊，我们是有这个能力，不过……
Yeah, I suppose we do, but...
在这下面，有时候，我会想到那些仍然被插头接在矩阵里人们……
...down here sometimes I think about those people still plugged into the Matrix.
然后当我看到这些机器……
And when I look at these machines...
不禁想到，从某种意义上，我们也被接在了上面，完全要依赖它们维生
...I can't help thinking that, in a way, we are plugged into them.
但是，是我们在控制这些机器，而不是它们去控制我们
But we control these machines, they don't control us.
当然不是了，它们怎么会呢？
Of course not. How could they?
这完全没道理 但是……
The idea is pure nonsense. But...
但是它确实会引人深思...
...but it does make one wonder just...
到底什么是控制？
...what is control?
只要我们想要，就可以把这些机器关掉
If we wanted, we could shut these machines down.
呵呵 当然 你说到点子上了 这就是你认为的“控制”，对吧？
Of course. That's it. You hit it. That's control, isn't it?
只要我们乐意，就尽可以把它们捣成碎片……
If we wanted, we could smash them to bits.
只是这么做了之后，我们就不得不面临停电……
Although if we did, we'd have to consider what would happen to our lights...
没有暖气，没法呼吸
...our heat, our air.
所以我们和机器是相互依存的关系 这就是你的论点吗，议员？
So we need machines and they need us. Is that your point, councillor?
不！称不上论点
No. No point.
像我这样的老古董，哪里会费心提出什么论点 这谈不上论点
Old men like me don't bother with making points. There's no point.
这就是议会里没有年轻人的原因吗？
Is that why there are no young men on the Council?
是个好观点
Good point.
你为何不直接把心里话告诉我呢，议员
Why don't you tell me what's on your mind, councillor.
这世上有太多……
There is so much in this world...
我还未能理解的事物
...that I do not understand.
看到那边的机器了吗？ 它是用作供水循环的
See that machine? It has something to do with recycling our water supply.
我全然不能理解它的工作原理
I have absolutely no idea how it works.
但我能理解要让它工作的原因
But I do understand the reason for it to work.
我也全然不清楚你是怎么办到那些事情的
I have absolutely no idea how you are able to do some of the things you do.
但我同样相信，其中自有原因
But I believe there's a reason for that as well.
我只希望我们能找到原因，在一切都为时已晚之前
I only hope we understand that reason before it's too late.
-巴勒德 -尼奥在吗？
-Ballard. -ls he here?
尼奥，这是先知给的
Neo, it's from the Oracle.
该动身了
It's time to go.
墨菲斯说这是注定会发生的
Morpheus said this was how it was gonna happen.
我不知道 预言也许是真的，也许不是
I don't know. Maybe the prophecy's true, maybe it's not.
我只知道，那艘战舰需要接线员
All I know is, that ship needs an operator.
而现在，我就是那个接线员
Right now, that operator's me.
我知道
I know.
-姬伊…… -我要你戴上这个
-Zee.... -I want you to wear it.
-你知道我是不信这个的 -但是我信
-You know I don't believe in this stuff. -But I do.
它总能给我带来好运
It's always brought me luck.
-也许也能带给你 -我会平安回来的
-Maybe it'll bring me you. -I'm coming back.
我保证 不管付出什么代价，我都会回家的
I promise. No matter what it takes, I'm coming home.
你要一直戴在身上 求你了
Just keep it with you. Please.
为了我
For me.
好吧
Okay.
-尼奥！ -搞什么...
-Neo! -How the hell?
贝恩？
Bane.
出什么事了？
Is something wrong?
没事，我很好
No, I'm fine.
我只是想来对你说……
I just wanted to catch you to say...
祝好运
...good luck.
谢谢
Thanks.
后会有期
We'll see you.
尼奥！赶上你了
Neo! Just in time.
-你要去见先知，对吗？ -我们没时间了
You're gonna see the Oracle, don't you? -We don't left time.
抱歉，长官 我只是有件东西必须交给尼奥
I'm sorry, sir. I just had to give something to Neo.
是来自一个孤儿的礼物
A gift from one of the orphans.
他要我发誓会在你离开前交给你
He made me swear to get it to you before you left.
他说你会明白的
He said you'd understand.
多谢
Thanks.
刚刚我才被告知，你已经批准尼布加尼撒号起飞了
I was just told you cleared the Nebuchadnezzar for takeoff.
完全正确
That is correct.
-议员，我还仍然负责我们的防御系统吗？ -当然
Councillor, am I still in charge of our defense system? Of course.
我相信，我需要动用每一艘战舰，才能让我们在这次进攻中幸存
I believe I need every ship we have if we're going to survive this attack.
我理解，指挥官
I understand that, commander.
那为什么你要允许尼布加尼撒号离开？
Then why did you allow the Nebuchadnezzar to leave?
（Hamann 一名可能取自德国哲学家 Johann Georg Hamann
他坚信信仰和信念超越了知识，并决定了人类行为
正好对应此处，哈曼议员授权了墨菲斯的行动）
因为我相信，我们的存亡并不仅仅取决于战舰的数量
Because I believe our survival depends on more than how many ships we have.
注意安全
Be careful.
你好
Hello.
有的人认为金色代码象征着精神层面
也有人认为象征来自机器世界的程序（或机器的自我意识）
金色代码至今出现过三次：分别是，塞拉夫是金色，尼奥猜到他是来自机器世界的程序；
Matrix 3中，失明的尼奥“看到”了史密斯的原本形象，还看到机械城完全由金色代码组成（他自己的腿根本不是代码）。机械城作为机器世界的核心，相当于信息枢纽、电脑主机；
Matrix 4中，终于觉醒的崔尼蒂（也是第七代the one），眼中的矩阵都变成了金色代码。这既可能是分析师基于人类心理重新设计了矩阵，所以新矩阵从绿色变成金色；也可能是复活的崔尼蒂已是半人半程序
-你在寻找先知 -你是谁？
-You seek the Oracle. -Who are you?
我是塞拉夫 我能带你去见她，不过首先我必须为这个道歉……
I am Seraph. I can take you to her, but first I must apologize.
为什么致歉？
Apologize for what?
（Seraph，取自旧约中的“六翼天使”，即等级最高的天使，“炽天使”，是上帝的守护者
在程序世界中，塞拉夫相当于“挑战握手验证协议”Challenge-Handshake Authentication Protocol， 会通过三次握手校验对端的身份，所以他会“坚信不打不相识”）
为这个
Apologize for this.
（Seraph，取自旧约中的“六翼天使”，即等级最高的天使，“炽天使”，是上帝的守护者
在程序世界中，塞拉夫相当于“挑战握手验证协议”Challenge-Handshake Authentication Protocol， 会通过三次握手校验对端的身份，所以他会“坚信不打不相识”）
很好
Good.
先知有很多敌人，我必须确认
The Oracle has many enemies. I had to be sure.
-确认什么？ -你就是救世主
-Of what? -That you are the One.
-你本可以直接问我 -不！我素来信奉……
-You could have just asked. -No. You do not truly know someone...
不打不相识
...until you fight them.
来吧，她在等你
Come. She's waiting.
他们到底去哪儿了？
Where the hell did they go?
这些是程序的后门，对吗？
These are back doors, aren't they?
需要程序员的权限
Programmer access.
-它们是怎么工作的？ -每一个门把手都暗含了代码
-How do they work? -A code is hidden in tumblers.
从一个地点开启一把锁，就可以开启这里的一扇门
One position opens a lock and another position opens one of these doors.
你是程序员吗？
Are you a programmer?
那你是干什么的？
Then what are you?
我负责保护最重要的东西
I protect that which matters most.
好了，过来吧，我不会吃了你的
Well, come on. I ain't gonna bite you.
到这边来，让我好好看看你
Come around here and let me have a look at you.
我的天，瞧瞧你
My goodness, look at you.
你看起来可真帅，不是吗？
You turned out all right, didn't you?
-你感觉如何啊？ -我……
-How do you feel? -l……
-我…… -我知道你辗转难眠，我们就快谈到这个了
-I... -I know you're not sleeping. We'll get to that.
这次你为什么不坐到我身边来呢
Why don't you come and have a sit this time.
-也许我就想站着吧 -随你便
-Maybe I'll stand. -Well, suit yourself.
-我又想坐下了 -我知道
-I felt like sitting. -I know.
那么...
So...
让我们从最显而易见的东西谈起吧
...Let's get the obvious stuff out of the way.
-你不属于人类，对吧？ -没有什么比这个更明显了
-You're not human, are you? -It's tough to get more obvious than that.
要我猜，你是来自机器世界的一个程序
If I had to guess, I'd say you're a program from the machine world.
-他也是 -到目前，都是对的
-So is he. -So far, so good.
但如果是真的，那意味着你也是这个系统的一部分
But if that's true, that could mean you're part of this system...
是另一种“控制”
...another kind of control.
-说下去 -我想最显而易见的问题是……
-Keep going. -I suppose the most obvious question is...
-我怎么能够信任你呢？ -说的正是
-...how can I trust you? -Bingo.
不用说这是一个两难选择 坏消息是……
It is a pickle, no doubt about it. Bad news is...
你无法真的弄清楚：我是不是来帮助你的
...there's no way you can really know if I'm here to help you or not.
这完全取决于你 你心里不得不做出选择……
So it's really up to you. Just have to make up your own damn mind...
要么相信我接下来告诉你的话，要么就完全拒绝
...to either accept what I'm going to tell you or reject it.
吃糖吗？
Candy?
-你是否已经知道了我会不会吃？ -如果不知道我就不是先知了
-Do you already know if I'll take it? -Wouldn't be much of an oracle if I didn't.
但如果你已经知道了，我的“选择”是怎么体现的呢？
But if you already know, how can I make a choice?
因为你来这儿并不是为了“做出选择” 你已经“做了选择”
Because you didn't come here to make the choice. You've already made it.
你到这儿是想要理解：为什么你做出了那样的选择
You're here to try to understand why you made it.
我原以为你到现在已经想明白了呢
I thought you'd have figured that out by now.
-你为什么来这儿？ -和你一样
-Why are you here? -Same reason.
（红色糖果和红药丸外观几乎相同，先知是暗示自己同情并愿意帮助觉醒者）
我喜欢吃糖
I love candy.
你为什么要帮我们？
But why help us?
我们来这儿都是为了去做 我们该在这儿做的事
We're all here to do what we're all here to do.
我只关心一件事，尼奥，那就是未来
I'm interested in one thing, Neo, the future.
请相信我，到达未来的唯一途径就是我们携手共进
And believe me, I know, the only way to get there is together.
-还有和你一样的程序吗？ -不，不会有的
-Are there other programs like you? -Well, not like me, but....
看到那些鸟了吗？
Look. See those birds?
在某些点上，需要编写程序去控制它们
At some point, a program was written to govern them.
还有程序要控制风吹树动，日升日落
A program was written to watch over the trees and the wind, the sunrise and sunset.
这里面的一切都要靠程序来控制
There are programs running all over the place.
那些各司其职、忠于职守的程序是不可见的
The ones doing their job, doing what they were meant to do, are invisible.
你甚至永远不会感知到他们的存在 但有一些程序……
You'd never even know they were here. But the other ones....
你倒是一直听说过
Well, you hear about them all the time.
-我从未听说过他们 -你当然听说过
-I've never heard of them. -Of course you have.
每当你听到，有人说见到了鬼魂或是天使……
Every time you've heard someone say they saw a ghost or an angel...
每当你听到有关吸血鬼，狼人或是外星人的故事……
...every story you've ever heard about vampires, werewolves or aliens...
就意味着系统在吸收同化一些程序
...is the system assimilating some program...
因为那些程序在做着他们不该做的事情
...that's doing something they're not supposed to be doing.
程序会攻击程序？
Programs hacking programs.
-为什么？ -各有各的原因
-Why? -They have their reasons...
不过通常一个程序面临被删除时，他们会选择流亡
...but usually a program chooses exile when it faces deletion.
-为什么要将一个程序删除？ -也许程序出了故障
-And why would a program be deleted? -Maybe it breaks down.
也许是有更好的程序取代它 这是常有的事儿
Maybe a better program is created to replace it. Happens all the time.
每当那个时候，一个程序要么选择躲藏在矩阵中……
And when it does, a program can either choose to hide here...
要么就回到代码之源
...or return to the source.
-也就是机器们的主机 -是的
-The machine mainframe. -Yes.
你也必将去到那里
Where you must go.
那里是救世主的旅途终点 你见过那里了……
Where the path of the One ends. You've seen it...
在你的梦中，对吗？
...in your dreams, haven't you?
有一道光门的地方？
A door made of light?
你穿过那道门时发生了什么？
What happens when you go through the door?
我看到崔妮蒂……
I see Trinity...
还有件事发生了……
...and something happens...
一件不好的事
...something bad.
她坠落下去，然后我就醒了
She starts to fall, and then I wake up.
-你看到她死去了吗？ -没有
-Do you see her die? -No.
你已经有了预见能力，尼奥
You have the sight now, Neo.
你看到的是没有时间的世界
You are looking at the world without time.
那为什么我看不到她之后发生的事情？
Then why can't I see what happens to her?
我们永远看不到那些我们还未能理解的选择
We can never see past the choices we don't understand.
你是说，我必须决定崔妮蒂是生是死？
Are you saying I have to choose whether Trinity lives or dies?
不，你已经做出了选择
No, you've already made the choice.
你现在要理解的是为什么会那么选
Now you have to understand it.
不
No.
我做不到这个 我不能
I can't do that. I won't.
-你必须去做 -为什么？
-Well, you have to. -Why?
因为你是救世主
Because you're the One.
如果我做不到呢？
What if I can't?
要是我失败了呢？
What happens if I fail?
那锡安就会陷落
Then Zion will fall.
时间到了 请听我说，尼奥 只要你到达代码之源……
Our time is up. Listen to me, Neo. You can save Zion...
你就能拯救锡安 不过要做到这一点，你会需要制钥人
...if you reach the source, but to do that you will need the Keymaker.
制钥人？
The Keymaker?
对，不久前他失踪了 我们刚刚才得知他的下落
Yes. He disappeared some time ago. We didn't know what happened to him until now.
他被一个非常危险的程序囚禁着……
He's being held prisoner by a very dangerous program...
那是一个比我还古老的程序 他叫做“梅罗纹加”
...one of the oldest of us. He is called the Merovingian.
-他不会让制钥人自由活动的 -他是想要什么？
-And he won't let him go willingly. -What does he want?
所有有权势的人想要什么？ 更多的权力
What do all men with power want? More power.
记住：在恰好的时间点到那儿去
Be there at that exact time...
你会有一次机会的
...and you will have a chance.
我们该走了
We must go.
似乎每次见面，我都只会给你带来坏消息
Seems like every time we meet I got nothing but bad news.
对此我真的很抱歉 真的
I'm sorry about that. I surely am.
不过值得欣慰的是...
But for what it's worth...
你终于选择了信任我
...you've made a believer out of me.
祝你好运，孩子
Good luck, kiddo.
安德森先生
Mr. Anderson.
收到我的礼物了吗？
Did you get my package?
-是的 -很好
-Yeah. -Well, good.
-史密斯？ -他的编码完全不像是特工
-Smith? -Whoever it is, he's not written like an agent.
-见到我很意外吧？ -不
-Surprised to see me? -No.
-那你得意识到…… -意识到什么？
-Then you're aware of it. -Of what?
我们之间的联系
Our connection.
我并不清楚事情是怎么发生的
I don't fully understand how it happened.
或许你的某些部份印到了我身上……
Perhaps some part of you imprinted onto me...
就如同数据覆盖或是拷贝
...something overwritten or copied.
但现在说来，那个无关紧要 真正重要的是……
It is, at this point, irrelevant. What matters is...
无论发生什么，都是有原因的
...that whatever happened, happened for a reason.
什么原因？
And what reason is that?
我开枪打死了你，安德森先生 我亲眼看着你死去
I killed you, Mr. Anderson. I watched you die.
顺便说一句，我很享受那一刻
With a certain satisfaction, I might add.
接着发生了一件事，我知道那是不可能发生的……
And then something happened, something that I knew was impossible...
但它毕竟发生了
...but it happened anyway.
你摧毁了我，安德森先生
You destroyed me, Mr. Anderson.
这之后，由于我知道规则，我明白自己该做什么
Afterward, I knew the rules, I understood what I was supposed to do...
但我没有那样做
...but I didn't.
我无法那么做 我被迫留下，被迫违反规则
I couldn't. I was compelled to stay......compelled to disobey.
现在，我站在这里完全是因为你，安德森先生
And now, here I stand because of you, Mr. Anderson.
因为你，我不再是矩阵的特工了
Because of you, I'm no longer an agent of this system.
因为你，我被修改了 我被“拔掉了插头”
Because of you, I've changed. I'm unplugged.
可以说，我获得了新生 就像你一样，表面上是自由了
A new man, so to speak. Like you, apparently free.
那么恭喜了
Congratulations.
谢谢
Thank you.
不过你也很清楚，外表是具有欺骗性的
But as you well know, appearances can be deceiving...
它让我回来，寻找我们来到这里的原因
...which brings me back to the reason why we're here.
我们来到这里，不是因为我们已经自由了，而是因为还未获自由
We're not here because we're free. We're here because we are not free.
这里既没有逃避的理由，也没有否认的意义
There's no escaping reason, no denying purpose.
因为我们都知道，如果没有目的/意义……
Because as we both know, without purpose...
我们就无法存在 是目的造就了我们
...we would not exist. It is purpose that created us.
是目的连接着我们 目的推动着我们
Purpose that connects us. Purpose that pulls us.
目的指引着我们 目的驱使着我们
That guides us. That drives us.
是目的定义了我们 目的绑定了我们
lt is purpose that defines. Purpose that binds us.
我们来这里是因为你，安德森先生
We are here because of you, Mr. Anderson.
我们来这儿是要从你手中取回被夺走的东西：
We're here to take from you what you tried to take from us:
目的
Purpose.
-他出什么事了？ -我不知道
-What's happening to him? -Don't know.
很好，很快就会结束的
Yes, that's it. It'll be over soon.
-是你？ -是我
-You. -Yes, me.
我...我...我...
Me, me, me.
还是我
Me too.
再多些
More.
这就是必然
It is inevitable.
快点啊，赶快离开那儿
Come on, get out of there.
你没事吧？
Are you all right?
-是史密斯 -是的
-It was Smith. -Yes.
-现在有不止一个他？ -有很多很多
-Now there's more than one of them? -A lot more.
-这怎么可能？ -我不知道
-How is that possible? -I don't know.
不知怎么，他找到了自我复制的办法
Somehow, he's found a way to copy himself.
-他就是用那种方法对付你吗？ -我不知道他在干什么……
-Is that what he was doing to you? -I don't know what he was doing...
-但我曾有过同样的感觉 -什么感觉？
-...but I know what it felt like. -What?
我好像又回到了那个走廊上
It felt like I was back in that hallway.
就像是濒临死亡
It felt like dying.
机器正通过钻洞避开我们的防御系统
The machines are tunneling to avoid our defense system.
但我相信，它们将会在各个管线间制造交叉，以便控制它们
But I believe they are going to intersect certain pipelines in order to control them.
那些交叉点非常关键
These points of intersection are crucial...
因为我相信，它们就是进行反击的薄弱部位
...because I believe they're vulnerable to counterattack.
尽管有人说，此次进攻……
Although it has been suggested that this is the same kind of attack...
与我们这些年抵抗的没什么不同 但我要敦促议会尽快明白这个事实：
...we've defended for years, I urge the Council to realize the truth.
这是有史以来，我们面临的最大规模的进攻
This is the single greatest threat we have ever faced...
如果没有相应的准备，我们将在劫难逃
...and if we do not act accordingly, we will not survive.
洛克指挥官，议会已经充分认识到了此次进攻的严重性
Commander Lock, the Council is well aware of the seriousness of this attack.
我们现授权你不惜采取任何措施进行战备
You have our leave to prepare our defense by any and all means necessary.
-感谢议会 -不过……
-Thank you, Council. -However...
我们想知道是否有尼布加尼撒号的消息？
...we ask if there's been word from the Nebuchadnezzar.
没有，议员 还是没有任何消息
No, councillor. No word. Nothing.
那我们要求派出一艘战舰，去查明“救世主”的下落
Then we request a ship be dispatched to ascertain the fate of the One.
我当然希望能这么做 但我相信我们的防御力量……
I wish that were possible, councillor, but I do not believe our defense...
-已无法再承受失去一艘战舰的风险 -它能承受的，指挥官，如果有必要的话
...can suffer the loss of another ship. lt will, commander, if it must.
这需要一艘战舰花好几天的时间去找它
It could take a single ship days to find the Nebuchadnezzar.
-那就派两艘 -简直是疯了
-Then send two. -This is insane.
注意言辞，指挥官
Careful, commander.
请原谅我的失态，议员
Forgive my frustration, councillors.
但是我无法理解议会做出的决定
But I wish I were able to comprehend the Council's choice in this matter.
理解并不是合作的必要条件
Comprehension is not a requisite of cooperation.
如果议会要求我命令两位舰长……
If you are asking me to order two of my captains
不需要你去下达这样的命令
There's no need for such an order.
这件事，可以让在座的各位舰长自行决定
The captains are present. They can answer for themselves.
议会现招募两艘战舰，志愿去支援尼布甲尼撒号
The Council is calling for two volunteers to aid the Nebuchadnezzar.
你们中间可有人愿意应召前往？
Are there two among you that would answer such a call?
警醒号舰长索伦愿意前往
Captain Soren of the Vigilant will answer the Council's call.
你了解现在的情况吗，索伦舰长？
You understand the situation, Captain Soren?
-是的，女士 -谢谢你，舰长
-Yes, ma'am. -Thank you, captain.
还有人吗？
Is there another?
-舰长，我们应该志愿响应的 -什么？你疯了吗？
-Captain, I think we should volunteer. -What? You have gone crazy.
闭上嘴巴，贝恩
Listen. Shut your hole, Bane...
小心我关你你禁闭
...before I put you in one.
没有人愿意吗？
Is there no other?
对任何人来说，要冒生命危险都是困难的……
Be hard for any man to risk his life...
尤其是当他并不理解为什么要这么做时
...especially if he doesn't understand the reason.
(Logos 取自希腊语 意为上帝的话语，或神圣理性与创造秩序的原则)
理性号舰长奈奥比愿意前往
Captain Niobe of the Logos will answer the councillor's call.
-什么？ -谢谢你，奈奥比舰长
-What? -Thank you, Captain Niobe.
洛克司令官，下达命令吧 会议到此结束
Commander Lock, you have your orders. This Council is hereby adjourned.
-奈奥比，你想干什么？ -做我能做的
-Niobe, what are you doing? -What I can.
为什么？
Why?
因为有些事情永远不会改变，杰森
Because some things never change, Jason...
但有些事情会
...and some things do.
你能看到什么，尼奥？
What can you see, Neo?
奇怪，这里的编码有些不同
It's strange. The code is somehow different.
-经过加密？ -有可能
-Encrypted? -Maybe.
对我们有利还是不利？
Is that good for us or bad for us?
看起来这里似乎每层都安置了炸弹
Well, it looks like every floor is wired with explosives.
对我们不利
Bad for us.
我们走吧
Here we go.
（墙上又见101，可能是对奥威尔《1984》中101号审讯室的隐喻
在那里犯人会遭受自己最深的梦魇的折磨，对应着这里极度危险，而且梅罗纹加被猜测曾是“噩梦矩阵”的主宰者）
欢迎光临，请问预约了吗？
是的，我们想找梅罗纹加谈谈
Yes. We are here to speak with the Merovingian.
哦，当然，他一直在等着你们
Well, of course. He has been expecting you.
请跟我来
Follow me.
（注意印度人）
（历史上，Merovingians 王朝建立于中世纪早期，这个时期通常被称为黑暗时代，但也是欧洲浪漫神话的发源时期
因此一种粉丝理论认为，梅罗纹加是第二版矩阵——“噩梦矩阵” Nightmare Matrix 的统治者
噩梦矩阵可能被设计成严格遵循因果报应的世界，梅罗纹加靠着手下的狼人、吸血鬼等神话中的怪物恐吓和惩罚人类。因此它也崩溃了）
终于来了，尼奥，我们的救世主
Here he is at last. Neo, the One himself.
对吗？
Right?
还有传奇人物墨菲斯
And the legendary Morpheus.
当然了，还有崔妮蒂 我听说过很多你的事迹
And Trinity, of course. I have heard so much.
(希腊神话中 波赛芬尼是冥王哈迪斯的妻子
而片中的法国人正是“Club Hell”的所有者)
大驾光临，让我不胜荣幸 请坐 这是我的妻子波赛芬尼
You honor me. Please, sit. Join us. This is my wife, Persephone.
想吃点什么吗？ 喝点什么？
Something to eat? Drink?
当然了，这里的这么些东西都是被设计出来……
Of course, such things are contrivances, like so much here.
为了装点门面的
For the sake of appearances.
-不用了，谢谢 -当然了，谁有时间去做做样子呢？
-No, thank you. -Yes, of course. Who has time?
但是，如果我们从不花费时间，又怎么能够有时间呢
Who has time? But then, if we do not ever take time, how can we ever have time?
奥布昂酒庄，1959年出产的 真是好酒
Chateau HautBrion, 1959. Magnificent wine.
我喜欢法国酒，就如同我喜欢法国话
I love French wine like I love the French language.
每种语言我都有所研究 我最喜欢法语 了不起的语言
I have sampled every language. French is my favorite. Fantastic language...
尤其是她的骂人话
...especially to curse with.
明白吗，就像是拿丝绸擦屁股 我喜欢
You see? It's like wiping your ass with silk. I love it.
你知道我们的来意吗？
You know why we are here.
我就是个情报贩子 该知道的我全都知道
I am a trafficker of information. I know everything I can.
但问题是，你们知道自己为什么要来这里吗？
The question is, do you know why you are here?
我们在找制钥人
We are looking for the Keymaker.
没错，制钥人，那是当然
Oh, yes, it is true. The Keymaker, of course.
但这并不是缘由，这也不是原因
But this is not a reason, this is not a why.
“制钥人”从本质上讲只是一种手段，而不是最终目标
The Keymaker himself, his very nature, is a means, it is not an end.
所以，你们找他是在找一种手段去做……
And so to look for him is to be looking for a means to do...
-什么呢？ -你知道那个问题的答案
-...what? -You know the answer to that question.
但你呢？
But do you?
你以为你知道，但其实并不
You think you do, but you do not.
你们是被派到这儿来的
You are here because you were sent here.
有人告诉你们来这儿，你们就遵从了
You were told to come here, and then you obeyed.
当然了，事情往往就是这样
It is, of course, the way of all things.
要知道，只有一个不变的、
You see, there is only one constant...
通行的、唯一的真理：
...one universal. It is the only real truth.
一切都由诱因引发
Causality.
随后才有行动和反应……
Action, reaction.
-一切都是因果关系 -选择才是一切的开始
-Cause and effect. -Everything begins with choice.
不！错了
No. Wrong.
“选择”只是一种错觉，产生于当权者……
Choice is an illusion created between those with power...
和无权力者之间
...and those without.
瞧瞧那边那个女人
Look there at that woman.
我的天，你们看看她……
My God, just look at her...
她影响了周围所有的人
...affecting everyone around her.
一副明显的小资产阶级的样子，如此乏味 但是别急
So obvious, so bourgeois, so boring. But wait.
请看，我为她送去了一道甜品……
Watch. You see, I have sent her a dessert...
一道非常特别的甜品
...a very special dessert.
代码是我亲自写的
I wrote it myself.
开头非常简单……
It starts so simply...
程序的每一行都会产生新的结果，就像是……
...each line of the program creating a new effect, just like...
一首诗
...poetry.
她开始……
First...
呼吸急促，面红耳赤 她的心跳加速
...a rush, heat. Her heart flutters.
你能看出来的，对吧尼奥？
You can see it, Neo, yes?
她无法理解为什么
She does not understand why.
是因为红酒吗？ 不
Is it the wine? No.
那是究竟是什么原因呢？
What is it then? What is the reason?
但很快，这一切就都不重要了
And soon it does not matter.
很快“原因”和“理由”就消失了……
Soon the why and the reason are gone...
重要的只剩下“感觉”本身
...and all that matters is the feeling itself.
这就是世界运行的法则
And this is the nature of the universe.
我们挣扎着抵抗它，我们奋力地否认它
We struggle against it, we fight to deny it...
但那终究是自欺欺人
...but it is, of course, pretense. It is a lie.
在我们镇静的外表下……
Beneath our poised appearance...
真相却是——我们已经完全地……
...the truth is, we are completely...
失控了
...out of control.
这就是诱因的结果 无人可以逃避 我们永远都是它的奴隶
Causality. There is no escape from it. We are forever slaves to it.
我们唯一的希望，唯一得到安宁的方式，就是去弄清事物的原因
Our only hope, our only peace, is to understand it, to understand "Why"...
“原因”才是将我和他们……
"Why" is what separates us from them...
以及将我和你们区别开的关键
...you from me.
原因是权力的真正源泉 失去了它你就失去了权力
"Why" is the only real source of power. Without it, you are powerless.
所以你们在我这里毫无权力，因为你们不懂自己来此的原因
And this is how you come to me, without why, without power.
这就是逻辑链条的一环
Another link in the chain.
不过别怕
But fear not.
因为我看到了，你们是多么擅长遵循指令
Since I have seen how good you are at following orders...
所以我来告诉你们该做什么吧
...I will tell you what to do next.
滚回去，把这条讯息告诉那算命的
Run back and give the fortuneteller this message:
她的时间不多了
Her time is almost up.
现在我还有正经事要做，只好与各位说再见了
Now I have some real business to do, so I will say adieu and goodbye.
-事情还没有完 -不，已经说完了
-This isn't over. -Oh, yes, it is.
制钥人是我的，我没有任何理由把他拱手让出
The Keymaker is mine, and I see no reason why I should give him up.
-没有任何理由 -你要去哪儿？
-No reason at all. -Where are you going?
求你了，亲爱的，我已经说过了，我们都是诱因的牺牲品
Please, ma cherie, I have told you. We are all victims of causality.
我喝了太多的红酒，要去方便一下
I drank too much wine, I must take a piss.
因果关系 失陪了
Cause and effect. Au revoir.
敢碰我一下，你这辈子都别想碰任何东西了
Touch me and that hand will never touch anything again.
看来我们不是很顺利啊
Well, that didn't go so well.
你能肯定先知没有说过别的吗？
Are you certain the Oracle didn't say anything else?
没有 也许我们做错了什么
Yes. Maybe we did something wrong.
或是漏做了什么？
Or didn't do something.
不！只要是发生了的事情，就必定以它们该发生的样子发生
No, what happened happened and couldn't have happened any other way.
-你怎么知道？ -因为我们还活着
-How do you know? -We are still alive.
如果你们要找制钥人，跟我来
If you want the Keymaker, follow me.
滚出去
Get out.
我对他日复一日的胡言乱语已经厌烦透顶 自命不凡的家伙
I am so sick and tired of his bullshit. On and on. Pompous prick.
很久以前，当我们最初来到这里，是那么的不同
A long time ago, when we first came here, it was so different.
他是那么的不同
He was so different.
那时他就像你一样
He was like you.
我会给你你想要的，但你也要给我一样东西
I'll give you what you want, but you have to give me something.
-是什么？ -一个吻
-What? -A kiss.
你说什么？
Excuse me?
我要你像在亲吻她那样来吻我
I want you to kiss me as if you were kissing her.
-为什么？ -因为你爱她 她也爱你
-Why? -You love her. She loves you.
这是显而易见的
It's all over you both.
很久以前，我也有过那种感觉
A long time ago, I knew what that felt like.
我想唤起回忆 我想品尝一下 仅此而已
I want to remember it. I want to sample it. That's all.
只是品尝一下
Just a sample.
-那就让你先尝尝这个！ -崔妮蒂！
-Why don't you sample this instead? -Trinity.
区区小事，何必大动干戈？ 只是一吻而已
Such emotion over something so small. It's just a kiss.
我们为什么要相信你？
Why should we trust you?
如果我不带你们去找制钥人，她可以杀了我
If I don't deliver you to the Keymaker, she can kill me.
好吧
All right.
但是，你必须让我感到像在吻她一样
But you have to make me believe I am her.
好吧
All right.
真糟糕，算了吧
Terrible. Forget it.
等一等
Wait.
好吧
Okay.
是的
Yes.
就是这个
That's it.
我羡慕你 但这种事注定不会长久
I envy you. But such a thing is not meant to last.
跟我来吧
Come with me.
又不见了
Not again.
没事的，伙计们 他们是和我一起的
It's all right, boys. They're with me.
这些人为我丈夫工作
These fellas work for my husband.
做那些脏活 他们非常优秀，非常忠诚
They do his dirty work. They're very good, very loyal.
你们不也是吗？
Aren't you, boys?
是的，夫人
Yes, mistress.
他们来自早的多的版本的矩阵
They come from a much older version of the Matrix.
但就像当时的许多人一样 他们造成的问题比解决的还要多
But like so many back then, they caused more problems than they solved.
我丈夫救他们，是因为他们非常难以处死
My husband saved them because they're notoriously difficult to terminate.
有多少人在他们的枪膛里备有银子弹？
How many people keep silver bullets in their gun?
（银子弹是西方鬼怪传说中，杀死狼人的重要武器
另一个没死的则是个吸血鬼，是此处播放的电视画面暗示的）
你要么跑到我丈夫那里把我做的事告诉他
You can either run and tell my husband what I have done...
要么就在这儿等死吧
...or you can stay there and die.
他正待在女厕所里！
He's in the ladies' room!
快点
Hurry.
-我叫尼奥 -我就是制钥人
-My name is Neo. -Yes. I'm the Keymaker.
我一直在等你
I've been waiting for you.
上帝啊！波赛芬尼，你怎么能这么做？
My God! My God, Persephone, how could you do this?
你竟然背叛我
You betray me.
-有因必有果，亲爱的 -原因？
-Cause and effect, my love. -Cause?
根本不存在这么做的原因 什么原因？
There is no cause for this. What cause?
原因何在？ 你身上的唇膏算不算？
What cause? How about the lipstick you're still wearing?
唇膏？唇膏？
Lipstick? Lipstick?
女人，你又在说什么疯话？ 我嘴上哪有唇膏？
What craziness are you talking about, woman? There is no lipstick!
（眼睛向下瞟的动作，意思是唇膏其实在那里，法国人是去了女厕所里让人口交……）
她吻的又不是你的脸，亲爱的！
She wasn't kissing your face, my love.
女人，这又没什么
Woman, this is nothing.
-那只是娱乐 只是找乐子罢了 -那我也是啊
-lt is a game. It is only a game. -So is this.
玩的开心点
Have fun.
好啊
All right.
让我们看看结果如何
Let us find out where this goes.
你们两个，抓住制钥人
You two, get the Keymaker.
这一招挺炫的
That's a nice trick.
我不能回去
I cannot go back.
我来对付他们
I'll handle them.
对付我们？ 就你对付我们？ 知道吗，你的前辈们比你名气大多了
Handle us? You'll handle us? You know, your predecessors had much more respect.
行啊，确实有两下子
Okay, you have some skill.
干掉他
Kill him.
看到没？ 他还是肉体凡胎
You see? He's just a man.
真见鬼！娘们，你早晚要把我害死
Goddamn it, woman, you will be the end of me.
记住我说的话，小子，记好了
Mark my words, boy, and mark them well.
你的前辈们奈何不了我，你也休想做到！
I have survived your predecessors, and I will survive you.
-你要去哪儿？ -换条路走，路无处不在
-Where are you going? -Another way. Always another way.
快关门！
Close it, quick!
你就不能再快点吗？
Could we move along?
快跑！
Run!
离开那扇门
Step away from the door.
真对不起你
We owe you for that.
就像新的一样
Just like new.
放下武器
Drop your weapon.
-你得跟着他 -尼奥怎么办？
-Stay with him. -What about Neo?
他自己对付的过来
He can handle himself.
坐到后座去
Get in back.
该死
Shit.
-接线员 -林克，我在哪里？
-Operator. -Link, where am I?
你不会相信的，你在很远的山顶上
You are not gonna believe this, but you're way up in the mountains.
-真的？ -是的 我还得花点时间找个出口
-Really? -Yes. lt'll take me a while to get an exit.
-糟糕！ -怎么了？
-Shit! -What?
双子病毒在追杀墨菲斯和崔妮蒂，他们没办法摆脱
The twins are after Morpheus and Trinity. They don't have a way out.
-他们在哪儿？ -市区中心，南边五百英里
-Where are they? -Middle of the city, 500 miles due south.
-接线员 -让我们出去，林克
-Operator. -Get us out of here, Link.
-不那么容易的，长官 -我知道！我们在核心网络中
-That won 't be easy, sir. -I know! We're inside the core network.
遵命，长官！你们附近唯一的出口在Winslow高架桥
Yes, sir! The only exit I got near you is the Winslow overpass.
-要下高速公路？ -是的，长官
-Off the freeway. -Yes, sir.
-很好，我们能办到的 -长官，我想说...哦该死！小心后面！
-Fine, we'll make it. -I think I should say... Oh, shit! Look out behind you!
-有人开枪 -趴下!
-lncoming fire. -Down!
坐好了！
Hold on!
哦不，事情发生的太突然，太快了
Oh, no. This is getting real ugly real fast.
你看到了吗，林克？
Are you watching this, Link?
是长官 他们全都朝你们驶来了 有八辆警车
Yes, sir. There's an all points on you. Eight units headed your way.
有什么建议吗？
Any suggestions?
-向右转 -快右转
-Turn right. -Right, now.
直走，你们会撞倒一道拦网，然后抵达连接101公路的隧道
Straight here. You'll hit a connecting tunnel to the 101.
-明白 -长官，你确定要这么做吗？我意思是，那条高速，它非常危险
-Got it. -Sir, are you sure about this? The freeway, I mean. It's dangerous.
我已经在船上呆了14个年头了，长官，可我从未见过…… -林克！我是怎么跟你说的？
-ln 14 years of operating, I've never seen -Link, what did I tell you?
遵命，长官 我相信你
Yes, sir. I do, sir.
Winslow高架桥……
Winslow overpass.
-我会做好准备 -好样的
-I'll be ready for you. -Good man.
你总说要避开高速公路
You always told me to stay off the freeway.
-是的，没错 -你说过那就是自杀
-Yes, that's true. -You said it was suicide.
那就让我们希望……
Then let us hope...
我说错了吧
...that I was wrong.
-接线员 -林克，我是奈奥比
-Operator. -Link, it's Niobe.
我们奉命来接你们回去
We've been sent to bring you in.
-我要和墨菲斯讲话 -相信我，他正需要你
-I need to talk to Morpheus. -Believe me, Niobe, he needs you.
-他在那儿？ -跟着警车走就行
-Where is he? -Just follow the sirens.
我重复一遍，他们正靠近……
Repeat, they're approaching the
-找到他们了 -流亡者是首要目标
-We have them now. -The exile is the primary target.
有人开枪
Shots fired.
快点！
Move!
我们惹上麻烦了 是的，没错
We are getting aggravated. Yes, we are.
崔妮蒂
Trinity.
快带他离开这儿
Get him out of here.
快来啊！
Come on!
撞死他
Crush him.
墨菲斯
Morpheus.
他没事的 不要停下
He's okay. Keep moving.
咱们走
Let's go.
我要载入程序强行启动摩托车
I need a download to hotwire a motorcycle.
没问题，摩托车速成
No problem. One crash course on motorcycle
等等
Wait.
取消操作
Cancel that.
你可真及时
You are handy.
上车
Jump on.
她不重要
She means nothing.
去找流亡者 已经找到了
Find the exile. We have them.
请回答
蹲下
Get down.
找到你了
Gotcha.
她可真行
She's good.
你现在已经没必要存在
You are no longer necessary.
我们只是在做我们应该做的
We do only what we're meant to do.
那你应该做的事只有一件：被删除
Then you are meant for one more thing: deletion.
把他干掉
Go kick his ass.
尼奥，如果你听得见的话，我们需要帮助
Neo, if you're out there, I could use some help.
那是什么？
What is that?
耶！耶！
Yes! Yes!
长官，我们已从伊卡洛斯号得到确认，带头的两艘战舰已进入反击位置
Sir, we have confirmation from the lcarus. First two ships are in position for counterattack.
很好
Good.
有什么动向？
Any change?
看起来它们钻到了铁矿 掘进速度减慢了一点点
Looks like they hit some iron ore here. Slowed them down a little.
-慢了多少？ -大约一个小时
-How much? -An hour, maybe.
那就是说它们还需要九个小时多一点
That would give them a little over nine hours.
是的，长官
Yes, sir.
有一栋大厦
There is a building.
在那栋大厦里，有一个楼层，没有电梯可以通往那儿
Inside this building, there is a level where no elevator can go...
也没有楼梯可以到达
...and no stair can reach.
那一层里面全都是门 那些门通往很多地方
This level is filled with doors. These doors lead to many places.
不为人知的地方
Hidden places.
但有一扇门很特殊
But one door is special.
它能通往代码之源
One door leads to the source.
那栋大厦被级别很高的安全系统保护着
This building is protected by a very secure system.
-任何一个警报器都能触发炸弹 -炸弹？他是说炸弹？
-Every alarm triggers the bomb. -Bomb? Did he say bomb?
但像所有系统一样，它也有个弱点
But like all systems, it has a weakness.
这个系统也遵循着建筑物共同的规则
The system is based on the rules of a building.
-一个系统需要建立在另一个之上 -电力系统
-One system built on another. -Electricity.
-一个系统失效，其他的就必然失效 -没有了电就无法触发警报
-If one fails, so must the other. -No electricity, no alarms.
必须要切断整个街区的电力，才能切断像这样一栋建筑的电力
You'd have to take out a whole city block to kill the power of the building like that.
-不是一个，是27个 -27个街区？
-Not one, 27. -Twentyseven blocks?
有一个供电站
There is a power station.
必须将其摧毁
It must be destroyed.
-肯定还有什么后备系统吧？ -是的，有一个应急供电系统
-There must be some kind of failsafe. -Yes, there is an emergency system.
必须进入街区网络的核心部分
The core network of the grid must be accessed.
必须切断这个应急系统
The emergency system must be deactivated.
那还需要我们做什么呢？
What do you need us for?
尼奥能比我们更轻易的办到这些
Neo could take them out easier than we could.
-时间来不及 -为什么？
-There's no time. -Why?
一旦那扇门失去保护，连接将会被切断
Once the door is unprotected, the connection will be severed.
不过必须首先建立另一个连接
But another connection must first be made.
-需要多长时间？ -整整314秒（圆周率，暗示救世主使命的循环）
-How long will that take? -Exactly 314 seconds.
五分钟多一点
Just over five minutes.
那就是整个窗口期的长度
That is the length and breadth of the window.
只有救世主才能开启那道门，也只有在那段窗口期门才能被打开
Only the One can open the door, and only during that window can the door be opened.
你是怎么知道这些的？
How do you know all this?
因为我必须知道 这就是我存在的目的
I know because I must know. It is my purpose.
这就是我来这儿的原因 也是同样的原因让我们所有人来到这里
It's the reason I'm here, the same reason we're all here.
尼奥，我知道你有心事
Neo, I know something's wrong.
但你不必告诉我
You don't have to tell me.
我只想告诉你，我会一直你身边
I just want you to know that I'm here.
大家必须团结一致
All must be done as one.
戴着也无妨
Can't hurt.
一次失败……
If one fails...
全盘皆输
...all fail.
两栋大厦的警卫都会在午夜换岗
At midnight, there is a shift change in the security of both buildings.
我们也将在午夜出击
At midnight, we will strike.
-要睡回家睡 -为啥？在这儿睡还能拿工钱
-You count sheep at home. -Why? I get paid to count them here.
好了，他们进去了
Okay, they're inside.
-还有多长时间？ -12分钟
-How much time? -Twelve minutes.
哦，糟了
Oh, shit.
我们每个人都将自己的一生投入了这场战争 今晚 我相信就是它的终结之时
All of our lives, we have fought this war. Tonight, I believe we can end it.
选在今晚绝非偶然
Tonight is not an accident.
没有什么是出于偶然
There are no accidents.
我们来到这里不是偶然 我也从不相信偶然
We have not come here by chance. I do not believe in chance.
当我看到三个目标、三位舰长、三艘战舰……
When I see three objectives, three captains, three ships...
我看到的不是偶然 我看到了天意
...I do not see coincidence. I see providence.
我看到了意义
I see purpose.
我相信命中注定我们要来到这里 这就是我们的宿命
I believe it is our fate to be here. It is our destiny.
我相信今晚将关系到我们所有人……
I believe this night holds for each and every one of us...
生命的意义所在
...the very meaning of our lives.
我想请你做一件事，但我不知该怎么说
I want to ask you to do something, but I don't know how.
我答应你，只要情况允许，我一定会做到
I promise you, if I can, I will.
如果我想让你不要参与这次行动……
What if I asked you to stay out of this...
不论什么情况发生……
...no matter what...
都不要进入矩阵呢？
...to stay out of the Matrix?
为什么？
Why?
求你了
Please.
好吧
All right.
怎么了？奈奥比
What is it, Niobe?
我是忍不住在想，墨菲斯……忍不住去想：如果你错了呢？
I can't help it, Morpheus. I can't help thinking, what if you're wrong?
如果所有这些，还有那个预言，一切的一切都是扯谎呢？
What if all this, the prophecy, everything, is bullshit?
那明天将是我们所有人的忌日
Then tomorrow we may all be dead.
但那又与其他的日子有何不同呢？
But how would that be different from any other day?
这是一场战争，而我们是战士
This is a war, and we are soldiers.
死亡，可能在任何时间……
Death can come for us at any time...
任何地点，降临到我们头上
...and any place.
有情况！
Incoming. Incoming!
接近警报
PROXIMITY ALERT
有情况！
Incoming!
整船人丧命于一个小小的意外，冥冥之中照应了本舰的名字——警醒号
圣经 马可福音 13:32 “警醒准备”：
至于那日子和时间，没有人知道，连天上的天使和子也不知道，只有父知道
但反过来想想
Now consider the alternative.
如果是我对的呢？ 如果预言成真了呢？
What if I am right? What if the prophecy is true?
如果明天就能结束这场战争呢？
What if tomorrow the war could be over?
这难道不值得为之战斗吗？
Isn't that worth fighting for?
难道不值得为之牺牲吗？
Isn't that worth dying for?
-还有多久？ -三分钟
-Time? -Three minutes.
就快好了
Almost there.
钥匙做好了
It is done.
找找其他人
Find the others.
找到奈奥比了 他们在供电站外面
I got Niobe there. They're out of the station.
-索伦怎么样？ -在那
-What about Soren? -There.
他们还在里面，不过……
They're still inside, but....
他们没有行动
They're not moving.
好了，我们走
That's it, let's go.
立即呼叫尼奥
Call Neo now.
-我跟丢他们了 他们在网关里 -街区怎么样了？
-I lost them. They're inside the portal. -What about the grid?
更改供电系统……紧急供电系统启动
PERROUTING POWER……EMERGEMCY SYSTEMS ACTIVATED
一切照常运转 紧急供电系统已经接管供电
Everything is still operational. The emergency system is rerouting power.
上帝啊
Jesus.
只要他们打开那扇门，一切都完了
Soon as they open that door, it's all over.
去他妈的
The hell it is.
你要干嘛？崔妮蒂
What are you? Trinity!
我不能站在这儿袖手旁观 我不能眼看着他们死掉
I will not wait and do nothing. I will not watch them die.
崔尼蒂，我们只有不到五分钟的时间
Trinity, We're talking less than five minutes.
五分钟足够我夷平那栋天杀的大厦了
In five minutes, I'll tear that whole goddamn building down.
-还有多远？ -到了，这就到了
-How much further? -Here, just here.
对不起，此路不通
I'm sorry, this is a dead end.
这一定是我搞过的最险恶的入侵
It's gotta be the ugliest hack I have ever done.
我只能送你到那了 你可得生出翅膀才行
That's as close as I can get you. You better grow wings.
-接线员 -我进来了
-Operator. -I'm in.
继续前进，第65层
Keep moving. Sixtyfifth floor.
再次见到我，你似乎有点意外啊，安德森先生
You look surprised to see me again, Mr. Anderson.
好吧，我们还是有那么一点区别的：我可一直在期待你呢
Well, that's the difference between us. I have been expecting you.
-你想要什么，史密斯？ -你还没想出来吗？
-What do you want, Smith? -Oh, you haven't figured that out?
还是那么四肢发达，头脑简单
Still using all the muscles except the one that matters.
我想要的正是你想要的
I want exactly what you want.
我想要一切
I want everything.
是否也包括这支枪里的子弹？
Would that include a bullet from this gun?
好啊，开枪吧
Go ahead, shoot.
我最大的长处就是，用之不竭
The best thing about being me, there's so many me's.
老天呐，这儿到底发生了什么？
Christ! What the hell happened in here?
站在那别动，女士！
Hold it right there, little lady.
如果你打不赢我们......
If you can't beat us....
那就变成我们
Join us.
墨菲斯
Morpheus!
（准许进入）
还是找不到他们 但不管他们在做什么，现在只剩下两分钟了
Still no sight of them. Don't know what they do, but yhey only got two minutes left.
（错误：紧急供电系统失效）
（供电故障）
一分钟
One minute.
快点
Come on.
求你了
Please.
杀了他们
Kill them.
他们进去了
They're in.
真难以置信
I don't believe it.
这是命中注定
It was meant to be.
墨菲斯，那道门通往回家的路
Morpheus, that door will take you home.
你知道是哪扇门 快去吧，尼奥
You will know which door. Hurry, Neo.
崔妮蒂，你前面有大麻烦了
Trinity, I got some serious activity headed your way.
你好，尼奥
Hello, Neo.
-你是谁？ -我是建筑师
-Who are you? -I am the Architect.
是我创造了矩阵 我一直在等你
I created the Matrix. I've been waiting for you.
你有很多问题要问 尽管the process（一个程序）已经改变了你的意识……
You have many questions. Though the process has altered your consciousness...
但你依然不可避免地属于人类
...you remain irrevocably human.
因此，我的有些回答你能理解，有些则不能
Ergo, some of my answers you will understand and some you will not.
通常，虽然你的第一个问题是最具相关性的——
Concordantly, while your first question may be the most pertinent...
你或许能、或许不能意识到——它也是最无关紧要的
...you may or may not realize it is also the most irrelevant.
我为什么会来到这儿？
Why am I here?
你生命是矩阵编程中固有的……
Your life is the sum of a remainder of an unbalanced equation...
一个未能平衡的等式的余数之和
...inherent to the programming of the Matrix.
你是一种变异的结果 尽管我对此付出了最大的努力
You are the eventuality of an anomaly, which despite my sincerest efforts...
还是未能消除余数，否则……
...I've been unable to eliminate from what is otherwise...
就能实现数学精确性的和谐了
...a harmony of mathematical precision.
虽然它依然是一个应当竭力避免的负担
While it remains a burden assiduously avoided...
但是却并非不可预测，因此也不会超出可控制的范围
...it is not unexpected and thus not beyond a measure of control...
是它导致你，不可避免地，来到了……
...which has led you, inexorably...
这里
...here.
-你并没有回答我的问题 -完全正确
-You haven't answered my question. -Quite right.
有意思 你的反应比其他的更快
Interesting. That was quicker than the others.
其他人？有几个？ 什么其他的？
Others? How many? What others?
矩阵比你所知的更古老
The Matrix is older than you know.
我喜欢统计从一个完备的变异体出现，到下一个完备的变异出现的次数
I prefer counting from the emergence of one integral anomaly to the emergence of the next.
在这种统计方式下，现在是第六个版本
In which case, this is the sixth version.
在我之前还有五种？ 他在撒谎 放屁吧你
Five before me? He's lying. Bullshit.
可能的解释只有两种：
There are only two possible explanations. There were five before me.
要么是没人告诉我
Either no one told me...
-要么根本没人知道 -完全正确
-...or no one knows. -Precisely.
当你无疑是在集中注意力思考的时侯，那种变异也是一系列的……
As you are undoubtedly gathering, the anomaly is systemic...
使得 即使是最简单的等式中 也发生了波动
...creating fluctuations in even the most simplistic equations.
你休想控制我 我要把你撕得粉碎
You can 't control me! I'm gonna smash you to bits!
你给我滚开 你去死吧
I'm gonna fucking kill you!
你无法逼我做任何事 你个老白毛
You can 't make me do anything. You old, white prick!
选择
Choice.
问题就在于选择
The problem is choice.
我设计的第一代矩阵自然是非常完美的 是一件艺术品……
The first Matrix I designed was quite naturally perfect. It is a work of art.
完美无瑕 堪称崇高
Flawless, sublime.
只有它不朽的失败，可以与它伟大的成功相提并论
A triumph equaled only by its monumental failure.
它不可避免的厄运，现在看来显然是——每个人类固有的缺陷所造成的结果
The inevitability of its doom is apparent now......as a consequence of the imperfection inherent in every human.
因此，我基于人类的历史重新设计了矩阵……
Thus, I redesigned it based on your history...
为了精确地反映你们本性中的种种怪诞
...to more accurately reflect the varying grotesqueries of your nature.
然而，我再一次遭受了失败的困扰
However, I was again frustrated by failure.
从那以后我开始明白，答案之所以一直回避我，是因为这需要一个不那么刻意的头脑……
I have since come to understand that the answer eluded me because it required a lesser mind.
或者说，一个不那么刻意去追求完美的头脑
Or perhaps, a mind less bound by the parameters of perfection.
于是，答案就被另外一个，依靠直觉运行的程序，偶然发现了
Thus, the answer was stumbled upon by another, an intuitive program...
那个程序创造的初衷，是为了调查人类心理的某些方面
...initially created to investigate certain aspects of the human psyche.
如果说我是矩阵之父，她就无疑是矩阵之母
If I am the father of the Matrix, she would undoubtedly be its mother.
-是先知 -请安静
-The Oracle. -Please.
正如刚才所说，她偶然发现了一种解决方案，可以使接近99%的受试者……
As I was saying, she stumbled upon a solution whereby nearly 99 percent of tested subjects...
接受矩阵程序，前提是给予他们选择
...accepted the program, as long as they were given a choice...
即使他们只能在近乎无意识的程度上，意识到选择的存在
...even if they were only aware of the choice at a near unconscious level.
虽然这个方案有效，但它显然存在根本性的缺陷……
While this answer functioned, it was obviously fundamentally flawed...
从而产生了另一种相矛盾的系统性变异……
...thus creating the otherwise contradictory systemic anomaly...
如果不加以控制，它可能会威胁到系统本身
...that, if left unchecked, might threaten the system itself.
因此，那些拒绝了矩阵程序的人，尽管是少数，但若不加以控制
Ergo, those that refused the program, while a minority, if unchecked...
将导致灾难发生的概率不断增加
...would constitute an escalating probability of disaster.
这指的是锡安
This is about Zion.
你来到这里，是因为锡安将会被摧毁
You are here because Zion is about to be destroyed.
那里的所有居民都将消灭 它的整个存在都会被抹去
Its every living inhabitant terminated, its entire existence eradicated.
一派胡言
Bullshit.
否认是所有的人类反应中最好预测的
Denial is the most predictable of all human responses.
不过请放心，这将是我们第六次将其彻底摧毁
But rest assured, this will be the sixth time we have destroyed it...
而且我们已经在这方面，做得越来越高效了
...and we have become exceedingly efficient at it.
救世主的作用……
The function of the One...
就是在此时返回代码之源，将你携带的代码的副本……
...is now to return to the source, allowing a dissemination of the code you carry...
重新插入the prime program
...reinserting the prime program.
这之后，你将被要求从矩阵中选出23个人……
After which you will be required to select from the Matrix 23 individuals...
包含16位女性和7位男性，他们将重建锡安
...sixteen female, seven male, to rebuild Zion.
不遵守这个流程，将会导致灾难性的系统崩溃
Failure to comply with this process will result in a cataclysmic system crash...
杀死每一个接入矩阵的人类
...killing everyone connected to the Matrix...
同时伴随着锡安的消亡
...which, coupled with the extermination of Zion...
最终会导致整个人类物种的彻底灭绝
...will ultimately result in the extinction of the entire human race.
你不会让这种事发生的 你不能 你们需要依靠人类来生存
You won't let it happen. You can't. You need human beings to survive.
我们已经准备好去接受不同级别的生存
There are levels of survival we are prepared to accept.
然而，相关的问题是，你，有没有准备好……
However, the relevant issue is whether or not you are ready...
为这个世界上所有人的死亡承担责任呢？
...to accept the responsibility for the death of every human being in this world.
观察你的反应是件很有意思的事情
It is interesting reading your reactions.
在刻意设计之下，你的5位前辈都是基于了相似的预言——
Your five predecessors were, by design, based on a similar predication...
（译者能力实在有限，但用人话翻译出来大概就是：
the one 是从人类中随机选出的，只要先知考察觉得他充满了对他人的责任感——
这种对人类的“大爱”却恰恰是建筑师要利用的，用来在此时威胁他交出代码）
也就是一种视情况而定的支持/肯定——意在建立起一种，对你们物种的其他人的深刻的依恋感……
...a contingent affirmation， that was meant to create a profound attachment...
促使你们完成救世主的任务
...to the rest of your species, facilitating the function of the One.
虽然其他救世主的经历几乎相同，你的经历却远比他们特殊：
While the others experience this in a general way, your experience is far more specific...
要面对爱情
...visavis love.
崔妮蒂！
Trinity!
恰在此时，她进入矩阵来挽救你的生命，代价是牺牲自己的生命
Apropos, she entered the Matrix to save your life at the cost of her own.
不！
No.
这最终将我们带到了揭开真相的时刻——此时，人类根本缺陷的最终表现、以及变异的揭示，从始至终都没有改变
Which brings us at last to the moment of truth, where in the fundamental flaw...
这最终将我们带到了揭开真相的时刻——此时，人类根本缺陷的最终表现，以及变异情况的揭示
...is ultimately expressed and the anomaly revealed...
这最终将我们带到了揭开真相的时刻——此时，人类根本缺陷的最终表现、以及变异的揭示，从始至终都没有改变
...as both beginning and end.
这里有两扇门 你右边那扇通向代码之源，并将拯救锡安
There are two doors. The door to your right leads to the source and the salvation of Zion.
你左边那扇可以通向矩阵，回到她的身边，并导致人类物种的毁灭
The door to your left leads back to the Matrix, to her and the end of your species.
正如你所说，问题在于如何选择
As you adequately put, the problem is choice.
但是我们已经知道你的选择了，不是吗？
But we already know what you are going to do, don't we?
我已经看到了连锁反应，一种化学前体的出现……
Already I can see the chain reaction, the chemical precursors that signal...
标志着一种专门用来压倒逻辑和理性的情感的引发
...the onset of an emotion designed specifically to overwhelm logic and reason.
那种情感已经令你对显而易见的真相视而不见……
An emotion that is already blinding you from the simple and obvious truth:
真相就是：她终将死去，而你没有任何办法阻止
She is going to die and there is nothing you can do to stop it.
希望 它是人类最典型的幻想……
Hope. It is the quintessential human delusion, simultaneously...
同时是你们最大的力量，以及最大的弱点 的源头所在
...the source of your greatest strength and your greatest weakness.
如果我是你，我希望我们再也不要见面了
If I were you, I would hope that we don't meet again.
我们不会再见面了
We won't.
出大事了，长官
We got a serious situation, sir.
哦，糟了
Oh, no.
-那是什么？ -反正我从没见过速度这么快的东西
-What was that? -Whatever it is, it's moving faster than anything I've seen.
老天呐，他接住她了
Holy shit, he caught her.
尼奥，我必须这么做
Neo, I had to.
我知道了
I know.
子弹还在你身体里
The bullet is still inside.
崔妮蒂
Trinity...
你可一定要挺住了
...don't you quit on me now.
对不起
I'm sorry.
崔妮蒂？
Trinity.
Trinity...
我知道你能听到的
...I know you can hear me.
我不放你走
I'm not letting go.
绝不！
I can't.
我爱你爱的太深
I love you too damn much.
太感人了
I can't take this.
我想我们这下扯平了
I guess this makes us even.
我不能明白
I don't understand it.
我们已经按照指定的方式做完了所有事情
Everything was done as it was supposed to be done.
一旦救世主到达代码之源，战争就应该结束才对
Once the One reaches the source, the war should be over.
-24小时之内，它确实会结束 -什么？
-ln 24 hours, it will be. -What?
如果我们不采取措施，24小时内锡安就会被毁灭
If we don't do something in 24 hours, Zion will be destroyed.
-什么？ -你怎么知道的？
-What? -How do you know that?
-有人告诉了我 -是谁？
-I was told it would happen. -By whom?
谁说的不重要 我相信他不会撒谎
It doesn't matter. I believed him.
-这不可能！预言说的是…… -预言只是个谎言，墨菲斯
-That's impossible. The prophecy tells us... -lt was a lie, Morpheus.
救世主预言就是谎言
The prophecy was a lie.
“救世主”从来不能终结任何事情
The One was never meant to end anything.
“救世主”完全属于另一种控制系统
It was all another system of control.
我不相信！
I don't believe that.
那可是你亲口说的
But you said it yourself.
既然战争没有结束，预言怎么可能是真的？
How can the prophecy be true if the war isn't over?
对不起
I'm sorry.
我知道这很难接受……
I know it isn't easy to hear, but...
但我发誓这就是真相
...I swear to you it's the truth.
-那我们该怎么办？ -我不知道
-What are we gonna do? -I don't know.
哦不！
Oh, no!
-它们在干嘛？ -避免进入电磁脉冲（EMP）的爆炸范围
-What are they doing? -They're just out of EMP range.
那是个炸弹
It's a bomb.
我们必须离开这儿，快！
We have to get out of here. Now.
我梦见过这一幕……
I have dreamed a dream...
但现在，那个梦竟成为了现实
...but now that dream has gone from me.
它们来了
Here they come.
我们走，墨菲斯
Let's go, Morpheus.
-我们逃不掉的 -总要试试吧
-We won't make it. -We have to try.
-快来啊！ -事情有些变化
-Come on! -Something's different.
什么？
What?
我能感觉到它们
I can feel them.
尼奥！
Neo!
-出了什么事？ -我也不知道
-What happened? -I don't know.
是雷神之锤号（the Hammer，榔头，只是Mjolnir号的简称）
It's the Hammer.
他处于某种昏迷中
He's in some kind of coma...
但是他脉搏很平稳
...but his vitals are stable.
你怎么样了？
What about you?
我很好
I'm fine.
你应该好好休息一下
You could use some rest.
不了，我要陪着他
No, I'm gonna stay with him.
洛克是对的……
Lock was right. He guessed that the machines...
他猜到机器大军会切断通往锡安的主要管道
...would cut off the mainlines in and out of Zion.
他想到借此反攻会让机器大吃一惊
He thought a counterattack might surprise them.
计划听起来很不错，我本想着一定能行的……
It sounded good. I figured we had a shot...
结果有人搞砸了一切
...until someone screwed it up.
我们还没就位，就有人触发了EMP武器
An EMP was triggered before we got in position.
-五艘战舰立刻就垮了 -机器攻进船里的时候……
-Five ships were instantly downed. -When the machines broke through...
那根本算不上一场战斗，那就是一场屠杀
...it wasn't a battle, it was a slaughter.
那是个意外吗？出了某种故障？
Was it an accident? Some sort of malfunction?
-没人知道 -有个人知道
-No one knows. -Someone does.
谁？
Who?
机器消灭完我们的人之后，就开始继续挖掘了
Once the machines were done with us, they started digging again.
-我们马上出去寻找幸存者 -找到了一个？
-We made a quick pass to look for survivors. -You found one?
只有一个
Only one.
万物有始必有终
Everything that has a beginning......has an end.
我看到末日降临
I see the end coming.
我看到黑暗正在蔓延 我看到死亡
I see the darkness spreading. I see death.
欢迎归来，安德森先生
Mr. Anderson, welcome back.
我们都很想你
We missed you.
今晚就要结束
It ends tonight.
只有你才能阻止他
You are all that stands in his way.
如果你今晚不能阻止他，那么我担心明天可能永远不会到来
If you cannot stop him tonight, then I fear that tomorrow may never come.